Guide to the Virginia historical documents collection, Late 16th century-1958
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Virginia Historical Documents Collection
16th Century-1958
C0034
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
2.25 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains historical documents relating to Virginia families and citizens. Documents range from pre-Revolution colonial documents to early 20th Century documents.
George Mason University
Oversize 1
Box 1
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Susan J. Brennan in 1985 and Dartmouth College Library in 1993. Additional documents acquired from various sources between 2005-2012.
Historical Information
Special Collections Research Center staff created this collection from small donations of historical documents.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Historical Documents collection was created out of many small donations of materials that were accessioned by the Special Collections Research Center over the course of many years. Documents range from late 16th and early 17th century Raleigh family letters, court documents from the 18th and 19th centuries, which include summons and slave receipts, and material from the Fairfax family. Also included are Mason family documents and Civil War letters. Lastly, there are 20th Century postcards depicting Colonial Virginia and a request answered by Senator Harry Byrd about attending the 1945 Presidential Inauguration.
Arrangement
Organized chronologically.
Related Material
The Special Collections Research Center also holds the
Index Terms
Persons:
Cook, Peyton; Fairfax, Denny Martin, 1725?-1800
Geography:
Virginia--History--18th century.; Virginia--History--19th century.; Virginia--History--20th century.
Subject:
Courthouses--Virginia--Fairfax.; Slavery--Virginia--Loudoun County.
Document Types:
Letters.
Contents List
  - George Wyley to Daniel Clarke, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Raleigh Family Letters, 1595-18th Century (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains one letter in French.
  - Fairfax County Bail Bonds, 1714 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lord Fairfax Land Survey, 1739 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John Park vs William Hall, 1746 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Settlement of debt.
  - Mary Tarbuck vs John Doones Court Summons of Witnesses, 1754 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    William Lyndin, John Lynnston, and Mary Bradford on behalf of Tarbuck.
  - David Hughes vs Joseph Stevens, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Joseph Janney, Leesburg, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Merchant's letter concerning the pre-Revolution shipping of goods.
  - Denny Fairfax Land Lease Document, December 4, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    100 Acres of Fairfax land leased to Alexander White of Hardy County.
  - William Alexander to Washington, December 21, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Rent of Land from Alexander by Washington.
  - Indenture of Hugh Ogden, Loudoun County, Spring 1815 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Hugh Ogden entered into the service of a miller as his apprentice.
  - Calvin Jewett New Year's Resolutions, December 29, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - James H. Reid Slave Holding, May 22, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Slave Deed of Gift Maynadier Mason, March 29, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Mason granting a "negro slave woman" to a maternal aunt of his deceased wife.
  - Peyton Cook Slave Receipt, January 14, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Receipt transferring ownership of Peyton Cook. Written on lined paper.
  - James M. Mason Letter to President James Buchanan, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rhode Island soldier Civil War Letter, July 15, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Letter by a soldier identified only as Frank at Camp Clarke, addressed to his brother and discusses orders to march, President Lincoln, being photographed, the Fourth of July, etc.
  - James M. Mason Letter on Trent Affair, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter from unidentified Confederate Soldier to his Mother, January 29, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Location is listed as "Camp Burton's Farm."
  - Jamestowne Exposition Postcard, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Postcard with Capt. John Smith and Pocahontas, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Harry F. Byrd Letter about Presidential Inauguration, December 18, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Envelope with Anniversary Gunston Hall Stamp, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fairfax County Sun Echo, September 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)